I've been telling people online in various ways, and in lectures,
that they should start fixing up the world by cleaning up their room.
And I wanted to just elaborate on that a little bit before I get back to the lecture itself.
So as it becomes this weird internet meme you know.
And it's a joke. And good, it's a joke.
I'm really happy about the fact that, so much of this has got like the leaven of humor in it and it's really important.
Because that's what stops things from degenerating into conflict is humor.
And let's say you want to sort out your room and beautify it, because the beauty is also important.
And let's say that all you have is just a little room.
Like, you're not rich. You're poor.
And you don't have any power, that's another thing.
But you've got your damn room.
And you've got this space right in front of you.
You know, that that's a part of the cosmos that you can come to grips with.
Then you might think, what's there in front of you? Right in front of you?
And the answer to that is it depends on how open your eyes are. That's the proper answer.
Because you could say ...
William Blake* said this for example, and Aldous Huxley made comments that were very similar.
That in a transcendent state, you can see infinity in the finite.
And you might say, well you can say, if you can see infinity in what you have within your grasp.
If you look and you could say maybe that's the case with your room.
So, you want to clean up your room.
Well, okay, how do you do that exactly?
Well, a room is a place to sleep.
And so if you set your room up properly,
then you figure out how to sleep, and when you should sleep, and how you should sleep.
And then, you figure out when you should wake up.
And then, you figure out what clothes you should wear,
because they have to be arranged properly in your dresser.
And then, you have to have some place to put your cloth on.
And if you're gonna have some clothes, then you have to figure out what you're gonna wear those clothes to do.
Right? And then that means you have to figure out what you're going to do.
And then, your room has to serve that purpose.
Because otherwise it isn't set up properly. And if it doesn't set up ... if it doesn't serve your purposes,
you will be unhappy, and not happy in the room.
Because the way that we perceive the world is as a place to move from point A to point B in.
And then, if the place that we're in facilitates that movement then we're happy to be there.
And if the place that we're in serves as an obstacle to that movement then we're unhappy to be there.
And, so, what it means to set up your room is that you have to have somewhere to go that's worthwhile,
or you can't set up your room.
And then, your room has to be set up to facilitate that.
And then, the next thing is, well, maybe you have to make it beautiful, but that's not easy, right?
That means you have to have some taste.
And that doesn't mean you have to have money. It doesn't.
Because you can be garish with money, and you can be tasteful with nothing.
All you need is taste, and taste beats money when it comes to beautifying things, you know.
I mean, not that money is trivial, because it's not, but taste is crucial.
And people who are very artistically oriented can make beautiful things out of virtually nothing.
And not only that.
The literature suggests that if you're going to make beautiful things,
putting real constraints on what you allow yourself to do facilitates creativity instead of interfering with it.
Because, let's say you have to make something out of nothing, right?
Which I suppose would be a godly act, right?
If you have to make something out of nothing, you have to be creative in order to do that.
And, so, then, it is, to beautify your room means that you also have to develop your capacity to be creative.
And, so, then you can make your room shine.
But then what will happen is that,
if your family isn't together they will interfere with that.
You'll interfere with that because you won't have the discipline to do it properly.
But then when you start building this little microcosm of perfection with what you have at hand,
then it'll evoke all the pathologies of everyone in your household.
They'll wonder what the hell you're up to in there.
And they won't necessarily be happy.
Because, if you're ... if they're in a lowly place, let's say, and so are you.
And you're trying to move out of that.
Then, the higher you move out of that, the more the place they're in looks bad.
And you might say, well, what they should do is celebrate your victory over chaos and evil.
But that isn't what will happen.
What will happen instead is that they will attempt to pull you back down. They'll attempt to.
And I mean, obviously, [not all families do that], but all families do that to some degree.
And some families do almost nothing but that.
And so what that means is that, if you're going to organize your room,
then you're going to have to confront the devils in your house.
And that's often a terrifying thing
because some of those devils have have lineages that go back many many many generations.
And god only knows what you will have to struggle with in order to overcome that.
And so, and then, and so, to sort yourself out and to fix up your room is a non-trivial matter, you know.
And, you can do that, you'll learn by doing that.
And then, maybe you'll learn enough by doing that, so that you can fix up your family a little bit.
And then, having done that, you'll have enough character.
So that when you try to operate in the world, at your job, or maybe in the broader social spheres,
that you'll be a force for good instead of harm.
Because you'll have learned some humility by noting just how difficult it was to put your damn room together.
Well, and yourself, for that matter.
And so, you'll proceed cautiously with your eyes open towards the good.