I've been telling people online in
various ways and in lectures that they
should start fixing up the world by
cleaning up their room and I wanted to
just elaborate on that a little bit
before I get back to the lecture itself
so as it's become this internet weird
internet meme you know and and and it's
a joke and good it's a joke I'm really
happy about the fact that so much of
this has got like the leaven of humor
and it's really important because that's
what stops things from degenerating into
into conflict humor and let's say you
want to sort out your room and beautify
it because the beauty is also important
and let's say that all you have is just
a little room like you're not rich
you're poor and you don't have any power
that's another thing but you've got your
damn room and you've got this space
right in front of you you know that
that's a part of the cosmos that you can
come to grips with and you might think
well what's there in front of you right
in front of you and the answer to that
is it depends on how open your eyes are
that that's the proper answer because
you could say and William Blake said
this for example and Aldous Huxley made
comments that were very similar that in
a transcendent state you can see
infinity in the finite and you might say
well you can say and you can see
infinity and what you have within your
grasp if you look and you could say
maybe that's the case with your room and
so you want to clean up your room well
okay how do you do that exactly well a
room is a room is a place to sleep and
so if you say your room ups properly
then you figure out how to sleep and
when you should sleep and how you should
sleep and then you figure out when you
should wake up and then you figure out
well what clothes you should wear
because they have to be arranged
properly in your dresser and then you
have to have some place to put your
clothes and if you're gonna have some
clothes you have to figure out what
you're gonna wear those clothes to do
right and then that means you have to
figure out what you're going to do and
then your room has to serve that purpose
because otherwise it isn't set up
properly and if it doesn't set up if it
doesn't serve your purposes you will be
unhappy and not happy in the room
because the way that we perceive the
world is as a place to move from point A
to point B in and then if the place that
we're in facilitates that movement then
we're happy to be there and if the place
that we're in serves as an obstacle to
that movement
then we're unhappy to be there and so
what it means to set up your room is
that you have to have somewhere to go
that's worthwhile or you can't set up
your room and then your room has to be
set up to facilitate that and then the
next thing is well maybe you have to
make it beautiful but that's not easy
right that means you have to have some
taste and that doesn't mean you have to
have money it doesn't because you can be
garish with money and you can be
tasteful with nothing all you need is
taste and taste beats money when it
comes to beautifying things you know I
mean note that money is trivial because
it's not but taste is crucial and people
who are very artistically oriented can
make beautiful things out of virtually
nothing and not only that the literature
suggests that if you're going to make
beautiful things putting real
constraints on on what you allow
yourself to do facilitates creativity
instead of interfering with it because
let's say you have to make something out
of nothing right which I suppose would
be a godly act right you have to make
something out of nothing it you have to
be creative in order to do that and so
then to beautify your room means that
you also have to develop your capacity
to be creative and so then you can make
your room shine but then what will
happen is that if your family isn't
together they will interfere with that
you'll interfere with that because you
won't have the discipline to do it
properly but then when you start
building this this this little microcosm
of perfection with what you have at hand
and it'll evoke all the pathologies of
everyone in your household they'll
wonder what the hell you're up to in
there and they won't necessarily be
happy because if you're if they're in a
lowly place let's say and so are you and
you're trying to move out of that then
the higher you move out of that the more
the place they're in looks bad and you
might say well what they should do is
celebrate your victory over chaos and
evil but that isn't what will happen
what will happen instead is that they
will attempt to pull you back down
they'll attempt to and I mean obviously
all families don't do that but but all
families do that to some degree and some
families do almost nothing but that and
so what that means is that if you're
going to organize your room then you're
going to have to confront the devil's in
your house and that's often that's often
a terrifying thing because some of those
Devils have have lineages that go back
many many many
generations and god only knows what you
have to struggle with in order to
overcome that and so and then and so to
sort your cell phone and to fix up your
room is a non trivial matter you know
and you you can do that you'll learn by
doing that and then maybe you'll learn
enough by doing that so that you can fix
up your family a little bit and then
having done that you'll have enough
character so that when you try to
operate in the world at your job or
maybe in the broader social spheres that
you'll be a force for good instead of
harm because you'll have learned some
humility by noting just how difficult it
was to put your damn room together well
and yourself for that matter and so
you'll proceed cautiously with your eyes
open towards the good
[Music]
you